{"tossups":[{"question":"The fact that the consonants in this word also appear in words meaning “mirror” and “flower bouquet” inspired the design of many mirrors and bouquets. Alan Gardiner theorized that this word originally referred to a sandal strap and had its meaning extended by the rebus principle. In a formula that likely referred to prosperity and wealth, this word is followed by wedja and seneb; that formula often appears after the names of (*) pharaohs. The phrase crux ansata [krooks ahn-SAH-tah] is sometimes used synonymously with this word. This word describes a hieroglyph representing the three consonant sounds that appear in a word meaning “life.” For 10 points, name this word for an ancient Egyptian symbol resembling a T with a teardrop-shaped loop at the top.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>ankh<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>ankh<\/b><\/u>","category":"History","subcategory":"World History","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":1},{"question":"Eliezer Ben Yehuda campaigned for this English word to be translated into Modern Hebrew as badura, but his suggestion lost out to a word derived from a root meaning “lust.” The two common Mexican Spanish translations of this word are identical except that one of them begins with the letters “j-i,” from a Nahuatl word for “belly button.” The Italian translation of this word is the name of a time (*) management technique in which a task is broken up into 25-minute intervals with breaks. In a case concerning the Tariff Act of 1883, called Nix v. Hedden, the Supreme Court determined that this word refers to a vegetable for customs purposes. For 10 points, name this word whose two pronunciations are rhymed with “poh-TAY-toh” and “poh-TAH-toh” in “Let’s Call the Whole Thing Off.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>tomato<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>tomato<\/b><\/u>","category":"History","subcategory":"American History","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":2},{"question":"In a poem by this author, a character explains that words break the air and cause it to ripple, which is why the title location is found between the heavens, the earth, and the sea. An alphabetical acrostic is used to structure this poet’s translation of a French Marian poem, commonly known as this poet’s “ABC.” The word “galaxy” is first attested in a poem in which this poet dreams that an (*) eagle carries him to a temple dedicated to illustrious people. This poet’s contemporary Thomas Hoccleve called him “the first founder of our fair language.” This author used a word meaning “a nice thing” that sounds like a word for female genitalia in a story about a knight’s quest to find out what women most desire. For 10 points, name this author of The House of Fame and The Canterbury Tales.","formatted_answer":"Geoffrey <b><u>Chaucer<\/b><\/u>","answer":"Geoffrey <b><u>Chaucer<\/b><\/u>","category":"Science","subcategory":"Other Science","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":3},{"question":"These three letters are used to spell the linguistically unusual name of an unincorporated community in San Bernardino County previously called Soda Springs. These three letters are used to spell a word commonly used as a metasyntactic variable in computing, which derives from a magic word from the game Colossal Cave Adventure. These letters make up a top-level domain introduced in 2014 and used by (*) Alphabet Inc.’s website. These three letters are used as a discreet warning that someone’s fly is undone. In a set of dispatches released by the John Adams administration, these letters refer to a trio of French diplomats involved in an international episode that preceded the Quasi-War. For 10 points, name these letters that denote the axes [AK-seez] in a Cartesian coordinate system for 3D space.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>X-Y-Z<\/b><\/u> [accept letters in any order; accept <b><u>XYZ<\/b><\/u> Affair] (The first two clues refer to Zzyzx, which is the U.S.’s alphabetically-last place name, and “xyzzy.”)","answer":"<b><u>X-Y-Z<\/b><\/u> [accept letters in any order; accept <b><u>XYZ<\/b><\/u> Affair] (The first two clues refer to Zzyzx, which is the U.S.’s alphabetically-last place name, and “xyzzy.”)","category":"History","subcategory":"American History","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":4},{"question":"In 2000, the American Dialect Society named this word the “word of the 20th century.” Bert Kelly, the namesake of Bert Kelly’s Stables, claimed to have been the first person to use this word in its modern sense. This word, which was first used in print in writing about baseball, likely derives from a slang term for “pep” or “energy.” The dubious theory that this word derives from a type of perfume used by prostitutes was advanced in a 2001 (*) miniseries by Ken Burns that covers people like King Oliver and Chick Webb. This word was originally spelled with a double “s” in the name of the group that recorded “Livery Stable Blues” in the Dixieland style. For 10 points, name this musical genre that originated in New Orleans and that was practiced by Sonny Rollins and Miles Davis.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>jazz<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>jazz<\/b><\/u>","category":"Science","subcategory":"Biology","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":5},{"question":"A collection of poems about these words was written by Stephin Merritt and illustrated by Roz Chast, and includes a poem defining one of these words as “that mesmeric force / we now know isn’t there.” A word for a Tibetan breed of cattle and a word for a hundredth of a Vietnamese dong are among the 127 words of this type that are listed in (*) SOWPODS [SOH-pods]. In 2006, the number of these words in North America increased to 101 with the controversial addition of a word for a Chinese life force and a slang word for pizza. Because of their usefulness for making parallel plays, these are the first words memorized by most beginning players. For 10 points, identify this set of words which are the shortest words that can be played in Scrabble.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>two-letter<\/b><\/u> words acceptable in Scrabble [or the <b><u>two-letter<\/b><\/u> words in the Official Tournament and Club Word List; prompt on “<u>Scrabble<\/u> words” before “SOWPODS”]","answer":"<b><u>two-letter<\/b><\/u> words acceptable in Scrabble [or the <b><u>two-letter<\/b><\/u> words in the Official Tournament and Club Word List; prompt on “Scrabble words” before “SOWPODS”]","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":6},{"question":"The scientific name of the thorny devil consists of this genus name plus the species name horridus, and was inspired by a line of poetry. This word is used metaphorically in the title of a 2012 Garry Wills essay about American gun culture that quotes a description of a figure “besmear’d with blood.” Otto Eissfeldt [ICE-felt] theorized that this biblical word is not actually a proper noun, based on its similarity to a Punic word referring to a type of (*) sacrifice. This word is used metaphorically to describe a figure “whose mind is pure machinery” and “whose blood is running money” in Allen Ginsberg’s “Howl.” For 10 points, name this word that is traditionally interpreted as referring to a god honored with child sacrifices.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Moloch<\/b><\/u> [accept “Our <b><u>Moloch<\/b><\/u>”] (Milton calls Moloch a “horrid king,” which inspired the scientific name Moloch horridus for the thorny devil.)","answer":"<b><u>Moloch<\/b><\/u> [accept “Our <b><u>Moloch<\/b><\/u>”] (Milton calls Moloch a “horrid king,” which inspired the scientific name Moloch horridus for the thorny devil.)","category":"Literature","subcategory":"British Literature","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":7},{"question":"Supporters of this language argued that a mistranslation during an 1860 murder trial contributed to the wrongful execution of two laborers who spoke this language, providing an impetus for the official recognition of this language in the country. Weavers who were native speakers of this language were targeted based on their pronunciation of the phrase “bread and cheese” during a 14th-century uprising. People who were unable to pronounce the words (*) “shield and friend” in this language were killed in a nighttime massacre just before the Battle of the Golden Spurs. During World War II, German spies were identified by their pronunciation of a place name in this language, Scheveningen [suh-HAY-vuh-ning-uh]. For 10 points, name this language that exists in a state of tension with French in Belgium.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>Dutch<\/b><\/u> language [or <b><u>Nederlands<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Flemish<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Vlaams<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>Dutch<\/b><\/u> language [or <b><u>Nederlands<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Flemish<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Vlaams<\/b><\/u>]","category":"History","subcategory":"European History","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":8},{"question":"A campaign launched in 2020 aims to eliminate eponymous and honorific names for these organisms, beginning with a name honoring the Confederate general John Porter McCown. These organisms can be referred to by standardized four-letter codes called alpha codes. The word “jizz” refers to the general impression given off by one of these animals. These animals employ a brain region called Area (*) X to learn the combinations of sounds which make up their vocalizations. People known as “twitchers” often maintain “life lists” of all the different species of these animals that they’ve seen. James Bond was named after an expert on these animals. For 10 points, name these animals studied by ornithologists.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>bird<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>avian<\/b><\/u>s; accept <b><u>Bird<\/b><\/u> Names for Birds; accept <b><u>bird<\/b><\/u> codes; accept <b><u>bird<\/b><\/u>-watchers]","answer":"<b><u>bird<\/b><\/u>s [or <b><u>avian<\/b><\/u>s; accept <b><u>Bird<\/b><\/u> Names for Birds; accept <b><u>bird<\/b><\/u> codes; accept <b><u>bird<\/b><\/u>-watchers]","category":"Science","subcategory":"Biology","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":9},{"question":"In Old Norse, words used for this purpose are called galdrar [GALL-drar]. A word used for this purpose is sometimes thought to be a parody of a Latin phrase from the Eucharist meaning “This is my body.” George Waitz [vites] discovered a pair of texts used for this purpose that are named for the town of Merseburg [MAIR-zuh-burk]. A word used for this purpose is often written in a triangle with (*) 11 rows, with one letter removed in each subsequent row. The pragmatics of words used for this purpose are analyzed in the last two parts of a 1935 ethnography by Bronislaw Malinowski [broh-NEE-swoff mah-lee-NOFF-skee] titled for “coral gardens.” A Danish entertainer with the stage name “Dante” used the phrase “sim sala bim” for this purpose. For 10 points, for what purpose are the words “hocus-pocus” and “abracadabra” used?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>magic<\/b><\/u> words [accept descriptions of words that are used in magic <b><u>spell<\/b><\/u>s or <b><u>charm<\/b><\/u>s or <b><u>incantation<\/b><\/u>s or other synonyms] (“Hocus-pocus” is sometimes thought to come from the phrase hoc est corpus meum.)","answer":"<b><u>magic<\/b><\/u> words [accept descriptions of words that are used in magic <b><u>spell<\/b><\/u>s or <b><u>charm<\/b><\/u>s or <b><u>incantation<\/b><\/u>s or other synonyms] (“Hocus-pocus” is sometimes thought to come from the phrase hoc est corpus meum.)","category":"Mythology","subcategory":"Mythology","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":10},{"question":"This phrase is a variant of a phrase introduced by Gilbert Plass in 1956. This phrase generates weaker feelings of negative affect than a common alternative, according to a 2014 report released by a Yale research center partly named for this phrase. A Bush administration memo by Frank Luntz advocated using this phrase because it is “less emotional” than an alternative phrase that was popularized by James Hansen in 1988. In 2017, a (*) DOE office whose name includes the first word of this phrase was banned from using this phrase in written communication. Many media outlets now replace the second word of this phrase with “crisis” or “emergency” to emphasize the severity of the issue. For 10 points, name this two-word phrase informally used interchangeably with “global warming.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>climate change<\/b><\/u> [accept Yale Program on <b><u>Climate Change<\/b><\/u> Communication]","answer":"<b><u>climate change<\/b><\/u> [accept Yale Program on <b><u>Climate Change<\/b><\/u> Communication]","category":"Science","subcategory":"Other Science","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":11},{"question":"The protagonist is excited to see this word after reading a note that says “Please turn to page 541 of this book.” An entrepreneurial resident of Westfield named Bud Lawrence makes money by filing a trademark on this word. Six self-styled “secret agents” sign an oath that “from this day on and forever” they will use this word and “do everything (*) possible so others will, too.” In the last chapter, the protagonist reads a ten-year-old letter which reveals that the apparent villain of the novel actually supported this word all along. To spite the fifth-grade teacher Mrs. Granger, Nick Allen coins this word to replace the word “pen.” For 10 points, name this nonsense word that titles a children’s novel by Andrew Clements.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>frindle<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>frindle<\/b><\/u>","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":12},{"question":"This philosopher developed a system for indexing commonplace books that involved shortening words to their first letter and the following vowel. This philosopher wrote that, if two people agree on the meanings of the words “bat” and “bird,” they cannot disagree about whether a bat is a bird. This thinker criticized the “affected obscurity” of the Peripatetics [pair-uh-puh-TET-iks] and the use of words without (*) “clear ideas” in a chapter called “Of the Abuse of Words.” Robert Nozick coined a phrase referring to this thinker’s “proviso” to refer to a feature of his labor theory of property. Though this philosopher used the phrase “white paper,” his conception of the mind at birth is usually described with the phrase tabula rasa. For 10 points, name this author of An Essay Concerning Human Understanding.","formatted_answer":"John <b><u>Locke<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>Lockean<\/b><\/u> proviso]","answer":"John <b><u>Locke<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>Lockean<\/b><\/u> proviso]","category":"Philosophy","subcategory":"Philosophy","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":13},{"question":"A character whose name starts with this prefix is first spotted by the vicar Clement Hedges, who provides Victor Quartermaine with bullets to kill that character. A word starting with this prefix denotes an artistic motif studied by Matthew Stirling and Miguel Covarrubias and characterized by cleft heads and downturned mouths. In old Germanic law, a compound starting with this word refers to the (*) money paid by a murderer to the victim’s family. In the name of an Olmec artistic motif, this prefix precedes “jaguar.” This Old English word for “man” was often combined with wif [weef] in an alliterative phrase. For 10 points, name this prefix that, in a synonym for “lycanthrope,” precedes “wolf.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>were-<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>wer<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Were<\/b><\/u>-Rabbit; accept <b><u>were<\/b><\/u>-jaguar; accept <b><u>weregild<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>werewolf<\/b><\/u>]","answer":"<b><u>were-<\/b><\/u> [or <b><u>wer<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>Were<\/b><\/u>-Rabbit; accept <b><u>were<\/b><\/u>-jaguar; accept <b><u>weregild<\/b><\/u>; accept <b><u>werewolf<\/b><\/u>]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":14},{"question":"In one sense, this word was coined by Ed Goodgold, who is also known for being the first manager of the band Sha Na Na; in a related sense, it was popularized by the title of a book by the aphorist Logan Pearsall Smith. A portmanteau that combines this word with the word “administrative” was first used in the 1930s. In a mock Georgic poem, this word is used as an epithet for a (*) goddess who is asked to “aid my song” and “through spacious streets conduct thy bard along”; that poem is by John Gay. This six-letter word, which referred to the lower division of the seven liberal arts in medieval Europe, comes from a Latin word for places where three roads meet. For 10 points, name this word that now refers to unimportant facts.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>trivia<\/b><\/u>","answer":"<b><u>trivia<\/b><\/u>","category":"Mythology","subcategory":"Mythology","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":15},{"question":"In a book titled for these things and jaguars, the person who coined their name wrote that he came up with the sound of the word before settling on the spelling. Bob McDonald hosts a CBC Radio science show whose name is a pun on the word for these things. Haim [hime] Harari coined the names for two types of these things which had been predicted by Makoto Kobayashi and Toshihide (*) Maskawa. These things were named “aces,” after the playing cards, by George Zweig, who independently theorized them. “Beauty” and “truth” are obsolete names for two types of these particles. A nonce word from Finnegans Wake inspired the spelling of the name of these particles, which was coined by Murray Gell-Mann. For 10 points, name these particles whose flavors include “charm” and “strange.”","formatted_answer":"<b><u>quark<\/b><\/u>s [accept The <b><u>Quark<\/b><\/u> and the Jaguar; accept Quirks & <b><u>Quark<\/b><\/u>s]  Note to players: The clues in this tossup refer to a bunch of otherwise unrelated words that are spelled the same.","answer":"<b><u>quark<\/b><\/u>s [accept The <b><u>Quark<\/b><\/u> and the Jaguar; accept Quirks & <b><u>Quark<\/b><\/u>s]  Note to players: The clues in this tossup refer to a bunch of otherwise unrelated words that are spelled the same.","category":"Science","subcategory":"Physics","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":16},{"question":"A song that explains the meaning of this word begins with an answering machine message improvised by Ana Matronic, who says that MTA should stand for “motherfuckers touching my ass.” This was the childhood nickname of Ruth Bader Ginsburg, bestowed on her by her sister Marilyn. This word is defined as a “party for calming all your nerves” in a (*) Scissor Sisters song. This word can refer collectively to the two main sources of Japanese mythology, since it combines the last syllables of their names. In a 2001 experiment inspired by the work of Wolfgang Köhler, most subjects associated this four-letter word with a jagged shape and the word “bouba” [BOO-buh] with a round shape. For 10 points, name this reduplicative name possessed by a witch with a “delivery service” in a Hayao Miyazaki [hye-ah-oh mee-yah-zah-kee] film.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>kiki<\/b><\/u> [accept “Let’s Have a <b><u>Kiki<\/b><\/u>”; accept <b><u>kiki<\/b><\/u>/bouba effect; accept <b><u>Kiki<\/b><\/u>’s Delivery Service]","answer":"<b><u>kiki<\/b><\/u> [accept “Let’s Have a <b><u>Kiki<\/b><\/u>”; accept <b><u>kiki<\/b><\/u>/bouba effect; accept <b><u>Kiki<\/b><\/u>’s Delivery Service]","category":"Social Science","subcategory":"Social Science","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":17},{"question":"A member of this movement claimed that the word “lily” is worn-out and that it should be replaced with a word spelled “e-u-y” in his Declaration of the Word as Such. The English term “beyonsense” is sometimes used to refer to the “transrational” linguistic experiments of this movement. An invented language based on sound symbolism, called (*) zaum, was used by members of this movement to write works like the libretto for Victory over the Sun. The poet’s right to “word-novelty” is defended in this movement’s manifesto A Slap in the Face of Public Taste, which was co-signed by the author of “A Cloud in Trousers.” For 10 points, Vladimir Mayakovsky belonged to what Russian literary movement inspired by a similar Italian movement that glorified speed and technology?","formatted_answer":"Russian <b><u>Futurism<\/b><\/u> [or Russian <b><u>Futurist<\/b><\/u>s; reject “Italian Futurism”]","answer":"Russian <b><u>Futurism<\/b><\/u> [or Russian <b><u>Futurist<\/b><\/u>s; reject “Italian Futurism”]","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":18},{"question":"This phrase was first popularized by Lenny Bruce’s standup bit “Father Flotsky’s Triumph.” This phrase is used in a joke about the Pope and Raquel Welch on a lifeboat in a TV episode that ends with Father Curtis saying this phrase before “I pronounce you man and wife” during Karen and Mickey’s wedding. Peter Mehlman co-wrote an episode in which a character says “No, I mentioned the (*) bisque” when another character complains that she used this phrase during the best part of a story. In a TV episode that also coined the word “anti-dentite,” George’s girlfriend Marcy uses this phrase to shorten her stories. A 1997 episode of Seinfeld popularized, for 10 points, what phrase used similarly to “blah blah blah” or “and so on, and so forth”?","formatted_answer":"<b><u>yada <\/b><\/u><b><u>yada<\/b><\/u> yada","answer":"<b><u>yada <\/b><\/u><b><u>yada<\/b><\/u> yada","category":"Literature","subcategory":"American Literature","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":19},{"question":"The amateur historian Alfred Hudd theorized that this word derives from the name of a 15th-century Anglo-Welsh merchant who served as sheriff of Bristol. The title of an indigenist novel by José de Alencar [zhoh-ZAY jee ah-LAIN-car] symbolically anagrams to this word. In a preface to the Soderini Letter, Matthias Ringmann wrote “I see no reason why anyone could properly disapprove of” this word. A satirical variant spelling of this word was popularized by the title of (*) Ice Cube’s debut album. This word, whose first recorded use is on a 1507 map created by Martin Waldseemūller [vald-ZAY-moo-ler], is thought to derive from the first name of a Florentine explorer named Vespucci. For 10 points, name this word that can refer either to a pair of continents or to the United States specifically.","formatted_answer":"<b><u>America<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>AmeriKKKa<\/b><\/u>’s Most Wanted] (The Alencar novel is Iracema.)","answer":"<b><u>America<\/b><\/u> [accept <b><u>AmeriKKKa<\/b><\/u>’s Most Wanted] (The Alencar novel is Iracema.)","category":"Fine Arts","subcategory":"Visual Fine Arts","packetNumber":6,"questionNumber":20}],"bonuses":[]}
